- Afternoon, everyone.
Thank you for joining us.
This is the panel discussion on electric vehicles
and autonomous vehicles.
I'm Pam Gutman.
I'm the Regional Director
for Advanced Transportation for the Bay Area.
So, my territory goes from Monterey Bay up to Santa Rosa
and out to Sacramento.
I work with all the transportation colleges.
Those are the colleges that have programs
in light-duty automotive.
There are 14 of them, oops.
Three heavy-duty diesel who are now transitioning
to heavy-duty electric and four auto body
and collision programs.
Today, we are going to be focusing on the world
of electric vehicles and autonomous vehicles.
I have been very, very fortunate
to be working in this very exciting industry.
Transportation is an industry
that has been going unbelievable changes in evolution
just in the past 10 years alone.
The CEO of GM once said, not too long ago,
that the next 10 years is going to provide more evolution,
more technological change
for the industry than the last 50 years altogether.
So, in terms of electric vehicles
and know some of you may be worried about the future
of electric vehicles, well, I'm here to tell you
that electric vehicles are here to stay.
The manufacturers have committed
and are deeply committed to electric vehicles.
And right now, in case you're thinking about statistics,
California, in terms of the percentage of cars
that are electric are over 20%,
and if you're looking for statistics,
'cause I know everybody's doing that,
look at the California Energy Commission website.
They are partnered with the laws
and they have all the statistics you'd ever wanna know about
electric vehicles, charging stations, how many trucks,
how many cars are electric, et cetera.
How many public transit vehicles are electric
and the charging stations accordingly.
So, the future is still very solid
and we're very fortunate today to have one of the top 10
EV manufacturers on our panel.
And we'll be talking with Rivian
and Rivian will be sharing with us the latest vehicles
and the things that are going on in Rivian's world.
We're also focusing on autonomous.
Autonomous, of course, for those of us
who live in the Bay Area,
we are exposed to autonomous vehicles all the time
and we are very fortunate to have one
of our longtime partners, Nuro,
talk with us about their autonomous vehicles.
We're also gonna be talking to UC, Berkeley,
I was very fortunate to have been given a tour
of their mobility hub,
which is on 140 acres site just south
of the Richmond San Rafael Bridge.
I was very impressed with what UC, Berkeley, has done.
I went to UCLA though. Sorry, guys.
But I saw immediately,
because part of my background was that as a futurist,
so, I'm always looking forward,
I'm looking down the road
and I saw that Berkeley is doing something really magical
with its innovation hub in transportation.
And this is a hub that will serve
and I think help our community colleges as well,
particularly when it comes
to the heavy-duty electric transit side
because our colleges don't have the space,
cost of real estate's very expensive,
and we don't have the facilities
to actually work on those kinds of vehicles.
And this is an area we might be able to negotiate
and talk with UC, Berkeley, about.
Also, we share students.
So, many of our students would love to go to Berkeley.
And by working with them at the Mobility Hub,
this might give them an opportunity for an internship
to get to know Berkeley and hopefully go to Berkeley.
I would forgive them if they went to Berkeley. It's okay.
- If I remember correctly,
I think the highest acceptance rate for UC, Berkeley,
is instate transfer students from the community colleges.
Is that correct? - Oh.
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- Perfect.
We are going to continue that record going forward.
And last but not least, I have the privilege
of having on the panel, one of my favorite faculty
and administrators from the community colleges,
Randy Bryant will be joining us.
And I've known Randy since the first day
that I started working in this position.
And he initially was department chair
of automotive at De Anza College.
Then he was dean and now he's been promoted
to Vice President of Economic Innovation
and Workforce Development.
And he has come up with some very innovative ways
that we can work effectively
with our partners in the transportation space,
especially our partners who bridge many disciplines of work.
Because the work of an automotive mechanic in transportation
has really evolved in the last 10 years.
It's not a dirty hands job anymore.
The laptop is the new toolbox.
And the work really requires our students
to have a good grounding across a number of disciplines.
And Randy has put together different approaches
that enable our college programs to work effectively
with our partners who have much more challenging work
and skillset demands than previously thought.
So, the forward future march of transportation continues on.
It's very exciting, it's thrilling.
I've been very fortunate to be in this field
and I'd like to start off the panel and have Rivian join us.
The panelists will each talk about their companies,
their vehicles, and then some of the issues in terms
of workforce challenges that they have.
And then we'll have a panel discussion.
Tom?
(chair clanking)
- Hello, everyone.
My name is Tom Clark.
Thank you so much for the introduction
to both the event and right now as well.
I am a Program Manager at Rivian
on the workforce development team.
So, I can speak to a really specific subset
of what happens within Rivian,
specifically workforce development
and the relationship that we have between us
and service or the L&D side in service.
Before I dive into more of an intro,
I kind of wanna play a video from Rivian
that talks a bit about the ideology
and who we are as a company.
(motor engine rumbling)
- [Child Narrator] What if your dream
was to build the fastest car ever?
(motor engine rumbling) (lively music)
Like it was the only thing you thought about.
- [Driver] Two laps to go.
- [Child Narrator] One day, what if you decided
to really do it?
- [Entrepreneur] I'm gonna start a car company.
- [Child Narrator] But what if the world needed
more than something fast?
So, what if you built something more adventurous
that could climb mountains and go swimming?
(water sloshing) (lively music)
What if you put a hole through the side of it?
(bell pinging) (lively music)
And you took out the engine so you could fit in more stuff,
and it got better overnight?
(lively music)
And it helped keep us safe.
(child grunting)
And oh yeah, you still made it really fast.
(person whistling) (lively music)
What if was all electric
(child laughing)
and super-friendly,
and built for the future?
What if people start to really like it?
I mean, what if they like it and she likes it
and even these guys like it?
What if the next thing you build even more people like?
And what if you get something crazy like this?
(lively music)
(mouse clicking)
Is any of this even possible?
- [Person] It's definitely possible.
- [Child Narrator] You'd probably need
a lot of smart people,
like really smart, to build it all and make it big.
I mean, would the dream keep getting bigger too?
What if you built big factories in America
so everyone could work together,
and like there was a kitchen
and a Yeti to watch the dog and vans with smiley faces,
and a flashlight in the door.
Because what if?
What if this whole wild adventure,
what if it was already happening?
(car engine rumbling)
And what if this is just the start?
(birds chirping)
- Woo-hoo. - Thank you.
(audience and panelists clapping)
- [Narrator] I caught my stepson spying on me in the shower
at the same time that my husband
used this trick to get hard.
I discovered something crazy with-
(audience laughing)
- I don't know where that came from. I apologize.
- AI. - Yes!
- [Audience Member] Hey!
(audience laughing)
(mic humming)
- We don't need volume anymore,
so I'm gonna go ahead and unplug that.
(audience laughing)
All right.
Yeah, so I think like we should start off talking
about where we are as a company currently.
Rivian started in 2009,
more relevant to us and where we are now
is the amount of growth that we've had and where we stand
for our workforce development needs currently.
Our first passenger vehicle, the R1T,
hit the roads in October of 2021.
And currently, or just last year,
we produced 52,000 vehicles.
And our workforce has grown significantly.
We're currently over 15,000 people employed.
So, it just kind of like puts into perspective the amount
of growth that we've had as a company
over a very short amount of time.
My role within Rivian, like I said, is part
of workforce development, more specifically part
of the technical trades program.
Gimme one second.
I'm gonna pull my slide deck back up.
(Tom sniffs)
(laptop clanking)
Maybe.
- Of course.
(bottle clanking)
- Okay, well, we can keep going.
So, our technical trades program, currently,
we have five locations across the country.
The goal is to take somebody
that is got some basic core automotive skills
and upskill them to very Rivian-specific
service industry standards.
And the objective is to really allow them
to hit the ground running
once they go into the industry.
Our programs are between eight and 20 weeks long typically.
The candidate profile we're looking for
is not super specific.
We're not looking for somebody with a ton
of technical skills.
Within interviews and colleges
that I'm talking to, generally,
the two words that I look for when I'm promoting
the program is I'm looking for attitude and aptitude.
I need somebody with some technical aptitude
that I can put in a position without fear
of them hurting themselves or somebody else.
And I'm really looking for an attitude
that aligns with the company culture.
So, some of the attributes that we would look
for within the attitude is curiosity.
They wanna understand why and not just follow steps.
Adaptability.
So, EV tech industry evolves fast
and we need people that can embrace change,
can easily absorb new concepts, professional standards.
That's a big change from traditional automotive dealerships
to where we are as a manufacturer.
Every one of our technicians are expected to be in front
of customers and interact with the customer base.
And not only just customer base,
but also interact with our engineering teams
and really have a cross-functional relationship
across all of the company.
So, we need somebody
that has that professional demeanor and attitude.
And then career ambition, right?
Somebody that sees the steps of the technical trades program
as a foundation for something much bigger.
Should we continue on or? - If you want to.
- I guess the question is more about the panel.
- Okay. (indistinct)
- Okay, I'll leave the rest for panel questions at the end.
(James laughing)
- Awesome.
(paper rustling)
(mic clanking)
(mic buzzing and clanking)
(chair clunking)
(footsteps thudding)
What's going on (indistinct)?
- Tom, thank you.
Now, we're gonna have Blake Williams from Nuro.
(mic humming)
- Don't concern yourself whether it's too much.
I will try to be brief and give an overview,
tech or no tech, but welcome.
Thank you so much for coming and thank you so much
for having us.
I'm incredibly excited to chat with this amazing panel
and everyone who might be interested around EVs and AVs.
So, Nuro has been around since 2016.
We were initially founded as a delivery company.
Autonomously, founders came from Waymo,
which you may have heard of and started this effort.
Over the years we've migrated
to full autonomy in many different vehicle platforms
and we're excited to have announced recently
our partnership with Lucid
and Uber to build a robo-taxi service.
So, all our vehicles are electric.
We started off with purpose-built delivery vehicles,
so no room for passengers, which is what allowed us
to actually get the first commercialization permit
in California to drive autonomously, which was exciting.
And in terms of current updates, you know,
I think we've made a big pivot from delivery to licensing
and are now, as I said, partnered with Uber
and Lucid to build a taxi service,
comprising, I think, 20,000 minimum vehicles
over the next five years or so.
So, it's an exciting time.
You know, we are operating in Las Vegas.
We have our own test track there.
We're operating around locally in Palo Alto
and Mountain View, where our office is, San Francisco,
as well as Houston.
And we did our first autonomous drive in 2018 in Arizona.
So, a number of different locations
in which we have vehicles and offices.
In terms of our workforce requirements,
I have to echo a lot of what I just heard.
You know, it's really about fundamentals and attitude.
It's about curiosity. It's about a desire to learn.
I think soft skills are massively underrated.
Communication, project management, time management,
organization, things like that.
So, certainly would reiterate that.
In terms of community college support,
which I know is the focus,
we've actually been incredibly lucky to partner
with Jensen and have a program specifically
for Nuro, which we are incredibly excited to continue.
So, I'll leave the rest for any questions.
But thank you so much for having me and for listening.
- Blake, thank you.
So, our next speaker is gonna be James Fishelson
from the UC, Berkeley, to take us
one step into the future, maybe more.
- Well, we'll see. (chuckles)
That is...
- Okay.
- We're sorry. - Where'd he go?
- That's the Nuro one
right here. - Yeah.
- Gimme a second, guys. Hey, everybody, how you doing?
I am James Fishelson.
I am the Executive Director at PATH.
We're a research center at UC, Berkeley.
Where do I do share?
(mic humming)
One second.
There we move this around
and let's, hopefully this should work, fingers crossed.
(mic humming)
Okay, sorry. Your computer. Would you mind?
- Oh, (indistinct).
- Or there's no more... - That's it.
- I'll start.
Sorry about that.
(Pam whispering)
Yeah, yeah, yeah. We'll see.
So, we've been around since 1986.
We have, what I will mention, the oldest
AV test track in the world.
We have been working on autonomous vehicles
and various forms of advanced transportation technology,
including electrification, AI, the list goes on and on.
Since then, we first started doing AVS in the late 80s
and including a bunch of demos in the 90s
and 2000s and up till today.
So, looking better or nah?
Nah, don't worry about it.
So,
(mic humming)
our mandate
is to help bring technology
from the research setting towards the real world.
So, we're always sort of in the middle of that TRL scale.
We also love working with community colleges.
Apologies that we couldn't have them with California,
but we were recently awarded,
waiting for it to kick off soon,
a big grant on rural autonomous vehicles.
That's partnering with a bunch
of community colleges throughout the southwest.
So,
(mic humming)
I am going to...
All right. Oh, we're looking better. There we go.
We just need to- - You can read off
of this. - But is it not sharing?
- No, it's not sharing.
- Ah! - I know.
- Hold on. Lemme try to fix it.
Oh wait. Oh no, I don't need to share it.
It's a presentation. That's what.
(mic humming)
Perfect. There we go.
There we go.
So, I can talk about EVs too.
I'm gonna talk a little bit more about AVS now.
So, before I was at Berkeley, I worked at Ford
then I got my PhD out in Michigan.
As you can tell by my accent, I am a New Yorker originally,
so please don't hold that against me.
(audience titters)
So, Henry Ford supposedly said, almost certainly though,
it's apocryphal, "If I had asked people
for what they wanted, they would've said faster horses."
This is true everywhere in new technology,
and you guys are all familiar with this.
As a general rule, the more revolutionary
and different the technology is,
the least like the precedent will appear.
And people are always wrong
with what it's going to look like.
Oftentimes the new technology is especially bad
at what it's replacing.
Think of a cell phone.
The original iPhone was great at a lot of things,
but it was absolutely miserable at making phone calls.
The actual flip phones were much better at that.
(mic humming)
We are at that sort of inflection point now,
especially with automated vehicles.
We're further along with electric vehicles,
but things are still changing.
If you want to go back to the origins of the car,
the very first cars were called horseless carriages
and they looked like horseless carriages.
The very first EVs were basically ICE cars
that they just put a battery in.
Didn't really take advantage
of the unique benefits of electrification.
We're seeing some small cool stuff like in the Rivian,
you have that whatchamacallit?
The throughput where the- - The gear tunnel.
- What? - Gear tunnel.
- The? - Gear tunnel.
- The gear tunnel where, oh, it looks totally different.
So, we have more storage space.
All these cars have fronts.
But one of the biggest things I want to really stress
with you guys is that people love
to predict 50 years in the future.
It's super easy to do that, especially with automation.
We have a joke in the field
that automated vehicles are only 10 years away
and it's been that way for the last 75 years.
I am not exaggerating that number.
If anything, it's understating it.
You first had automated vehicles pitched
as a solution at the 1939 World's Fair
by GM's Futurama exhibit.
This is a more recent picture from GM.
This is what automated is,
this is what they thought automated vehicles
would look like in 1950.
Now, we have automated,
thanks to companies like Nuro, Waymo, et cetera,
we do have automated vehicles on the road today.
But what they will look like, how they will be used,
we don't know.
This creates problems
and challenges from a workforce development perspective
because it's not like I can say, "Oh great, we need
to be training workers for AVs.
They need to learn A, B and C."
It's like, well, what type of AVs are we talking about?
Are we trying to provide workers
for Waymo-type solutions, which would be fully owned
and operated, self-driving fleets of taxis at an L4?
That's fully autonomous level.
Or are we talking about supporting the OEMs in building
more ADAS-like technologies?
Those would be driver-assist technologies,
including the, perhaps inappropriately named,
full self-driving supervised.
Thank you.
(audience chuckles)
So,
(mic humming)
this is why we are hoping
to help play a role in bringing folks together
and learning together
and trying to train the next generation of people,
while keeping in mind just how uncertain this space is.
Now, as I'm going through, I want you
to think about two main things.
One,
is, what is the relationship between the driver
and the vehicle when it's an autonomous vehicle?
So, this works in two different ways.
One, and we're seeing this with a lot
of the AV companies now,
what does a higher driver do besides driving?
It turns out, quite a lot.
So, the famous line with Waymo's is they're driverless.
They are very, very far from laborless.
There is a lot of work
and energy that needs
to go into making a Waymo drive itself.
And even in day-to-day operations, somebody needs
to plug it into a charger, somebody needs to clean it.
There's a lot that goes into it.
There is a flip side to that question though,
is, why the heck are we automating this in the first place?
Automation tends to be a very expensive
and hardware-intensive technology,
especially for the full automation level four,
an obscene number of sensors
and an obscene number of incredibly smart people,
like my friend here,
who have to work on this stuff.
It is not cheap to make a vehicle drive itself,
especially now, can cost come down in the future?
Of course, but it's coming down from a high point.
And I want to say this in as nice way as possible
'cause I'm trying to keep politics out of it,
but, traditionally, drivers have been one
of the more abused segments of the population.
They tend to be paid pretty gosh-darn poorly
with a very few exceptions, with very few labor protections.
Taxi drivers, Uber drivers being a classic example of that.
So, you're trying to use a really expensive technology
on a one-to-one basis
to replace what is a very lowly paid worker.
It's the same reason, you can make an argument that,
well, it's the same reason why McDonald's
still hires a lot of people.
It's not that you couldn't build a robot to flip burgers.
It's that it turns out the person to flip the burgers
is more effective and efficient and cheaper
than building a robot to do it.
So, whenever anyone says, "Oh, we can just automate it,"
the first question you need to ask is, could we do this
with a human driver?
And if not, why haven't we done it already?
Now, that gets me to my second question is,
is this a genuinely new task, a new technology?
Is this vehicle operating in a fundamentally different way
than it did before?
And does that mean that we are gonna need new labor
and support, again, with an AV that I was just describing?
Yeah, it doesn't have a driver.
So, we need to have a whole other set of folks who need
to be involved with working with the sensors,
calibrating the sensors, cleaning the vehicles, checking in.
This is a new job that is absolutely required
because of automation.
There are many more beyond that, by the way.
I'm mentioning this to you guys,
and again, I'm trying not to get too political here,
but it is a risk with any new technology
that it's not actually the technology that is...
It's not actually the job that's changing,
it's just financial engineering.
So, and oftentimes that comes as well
with a de-skilling of labor.
So, I would argue that there are functional differences,
say with an Uber technology versus a taxi driver technology.
But the basic driver is doing the exact same thing.
The difference is a taxi driver needs to be licensed,
registered, pass tests, et cetera.
Uber was very effective at de-skilling the taxi driver work
where anybody can do that.
You are seeing this now with automation,
even just as a lobbying technique with unions
where, well, we don't need you anymore.
You know, don't push too hard on the next union contract,
truck drivers, 'cause we're just gonna automate you out
of existence if you push too hard.
Or there are middle grounds there, maybe we'll just descale,
you don't need a CDL anymore.
If you get this level two technology, any random person
with a personal driver's license
can drive a truck reasonably safely.
That is the job still exists, but it's now a de-skilled job.
So, these are things I want you to be keeping in mind
as I'm going through
and I'm now, I'm gonna be talking about the more fun stuff,
which is what you were just mentioning,
which is (claps) the big campus and effort
we have at Richmond Field Station.
So, I'm assuming a bunch of you have been up to Berkeley
or you're at least familiar with it,
I'm guessing fewer of you have been up
to Richmond Field Station,
which is about 10 miles north of camp...
A little less, seven miles north of campus.
And it is a big facility, quite beautiful,
right on the water, almost 200 acres.
And we've been using it as a research test bed for lots
and lots of things such as we have the state's largest
earthquake quake table there as an example.
We are in the process, and shout out to Justin in the back,
who is leading this effort,
thanks, Justin, to be building an innovative mobility
research hub where we're gonna be bringing in public sector,
private sector and academia to develop
and test a lot of these new technologies.
And we really think that workforce development
is a key part of that.
That's why I'm here today.
So, here is the overall vision.
It's gonna have some startup, I'm gonna go quicker
'cause I know I'm running outta time, startup incubation,
advanced research, tech commercialization,
all working together.
We have a lot of state funders involved
and interested already.
Just moving ahead quickly, we are covering lots.
My specific focus is obviously gonna be on land mobility,
but we also have a sea mobility component
and we will have one of the very few drone parks.
So, we're really excited to work with our close partners
in the drone space.
This is the RFS area.
This is what it looks like.
We just finished updating our AV test track.
We have a connected vehicle lab.
We have a lot of really fun stuff here.
We have an, sorry, I'm just running through.
I can share these slides to everyone.
We have a number of innovation zones.
We are partnering with GoMentum,
which is a big testing facility nearby
in Contra Costa County where they're also doing AV testing.
We're going to bring some of that AV testing to us.
And then I think the, to wrap up on this then,
I wanna mention to everybody
that we are having a big event,
sort of a coming out party on October 23rd and 24th.
We're calling it Drive AI.
First day is going to be a workshop
focused on AI in mobility.
Second day will be a demo day here out at RFS.
So, consider this your invitation
and also if you have any technology
that you would like to be demonstrating,
especially on day two,
please either hit me or Justin up.
So, I know I took up too much time,
so thank you so much, guys.
(audience and panelists clapping)
- James, thank you.
And next we have Randy
to talk about- - Sorry.
- Some of the innovative work
that he's been doing on the college front
with our employers.
Randy.
- All right, I think I'm gonna save you
from the PowerPoint thing, so.
(audience laughing)
I'm just gonna talk.
- Thank you. - So, I'm Randy Bryant,
I'm the Vice President of Workforce Innovation
and Economic Advancement at De Anza college.
And we're just a few miles away from here
for those of you don't know.
And I'm gonna bring it down to a little different level
and I'm gonna talk about what we do at De Anza.
And Team Deza and I support
about 24 different workforce programs.
And one of those happens to be automotive technology.
And we have a partnership with Nuro
and I'll tell you a little bit of how that happened.
That was really a mind-blowing, earth-shattering partnership
that we came with.
We went to and talked with a company at the time was looking
for four year degree technicians to work on their cars.
And we found out what they really were after,
and we found out what we already offered,
and then we said, "Well, we already offer all those classes,
why don't we repackage them
and then we can have a certificate
for autonomous driving vehicle technicians."
And they said, "Yeah, that sounds good
and let's go one step further.
We're really interested in diversifying our workforce
and that kind of thing."
And I said, "Well, how about if we make the entry-level
technician certificate non-credit,
would you go there?"
And they said, "Yeah, we'll go there."
And that was like, gimme some oxygen.
You know, how does that work?
So, it's just astonishing the partnership
that we developed there.
From that, other companies have talked
to us about spinning off
from that autonomous driving vehicle certificate
and doing other things.
One of the things that came up in the process
is that different companies would come
and talk to us about...
This ain't working.
I don't think it's working.
So, I don't know if we...
I'll use my teacher voice.
(audience tittering)
So, they would come and say, you know,
"We have this thing but we don't have..."
Is that better?
Okay, there you go.
So, "But we need to add this to what you're training,"
and the community college system is notoriously slow
for developing curriculum.
Well, we can develop the curriculum,
but by the time it gets through the process
and gets through the college process, it's a year
to two years before we can offer the courses.
So, we did a lot of streamlining in the non-credit world
where we can offer that quickly
and we're working at that.
But we also stood up a contract education not for credit,
where we can take our basic program,
which is a two year certificate
or a degree in autonomous driving
and add any company's proprietary training
in the contract ed section.
We can use our instructors, their instructors,
we can teach it at our facility,
we can teach it at their facility, it doesn't matter.
So, all of those kind of conversations
came from the Nuro partnership that we did.
And it's really astonishing
and the opportunities that it brings to our students
and to a lot of our favorite students
in automotive test students, of course,
you know that is a option that didn't exist before.
So, it was really astonishing and I applaud Nuro
for leaning forward to that.
But to go from a four year engineering degree requirement
all the way to a non-credit entry level certificate
opened up doors
to our most marginalized students and opportunity.
We have so many brilliant young people
that aren't gonna ever be able to go to Berkeley
or San Jose State or anything else because of life, right?
But they're brilliant people
and if we give them the opportunity, they will succeed
and be great.
And Nuro has really helped with that program.
So,
so far we've got nine students
that have completed the certificate
and another six, no, another eight that are in process now.
So, we're moving forward,
and those students are coming out of the pipeline now,
and so hopefully for Rivian and Nuro
and others, we'll be able to help them fulfill that need.
Now, they translate all the way across
the whole spectrum, which is eVTOL, right?
That's the vertical landing and takeoff vehicles,
that's cars, that's trucks.
They go across the whole spectrum
and then they can go into Berkeley
and work at the Richmond thing
and get into battery production.
There's so much is gonna be required in the near future
and we're on the way and have a program established
and we just gotta grow it.
The other piece that's really important
about the community college system and the training
that we can provide
is the partnership that we have as a community of colleges.
You know, like Silicon Valley colleges
are all working together now
in the industrial automation area to develop
programs where you could take a little bit
from this college, a little bit from that college
and put it together and make a certificate or a degree.
And that's like, that's new and exciting, (laughs)
basically earth-shattering.
We're all in the same room and we talk
to each other and we're nice to each other.
So, it's pretty good.
(audience member laughing)
But it opens doors for companies
to be able to package new stuff quickly
because the curriculum already exists.
We just have to package it amongst the colleges,
just like we have within each college.
So, it's really an exciting time to be at De Anza College
and providing technicians for these companies.
So, thanks.
(audience and panelists clapping)
- Randy, did you wanna talk about
the bachelor's program at all?
(James laughing)
- Just- - Yeah, that's another
great thing, that's...
So this fall, we're gonna start offering a bachelor's degree
in automotive management, which is another great thing
for students that may not be able to get to some
of the other universities.
So,
we've already filled one cohort
and we have a second one on the waiting list, waiting to go.
And we're trying to figure out how we're gonna do that.
So many cohorts of that, but it's really, really innate.
So yeah, thanks.
- What I loved about what Randy did is he combined
existing automotive classes
with existing computer science classes to meet
what Nuro required, the combination across
disciplines actually happened.
And for me that's very exciting
because that's something really new
and got people out of their silos
because that's what this industry needs.
The transportation industry is really requiring skill sets
across a number of disciplines for many of those jobs.
So, what Randy has started at De Anza College,
I hope will only serve as a template
for what some of the other colleges can do going forward
with our partners, because our partners,
sitting next to me, are very important
and critical components of the success
of our students going forward.
And I want Tom to talk
to us a little bit more, in more detail about
the trade skills program and the types of additional courses
and work that Rivian is looking for from the students
and the skill sets that you're looking for.
Thank you. Tom.
Oh, sorry. - Sorry.
(mic squeaking)
- To be clear, Nuro still gets first dibs, yeah?
(audience and Pam laughing)
- Yeah, so I think we all touched on it a little bit
and what we're looking for are the skill sets required,
as mentioned during my presentation, we're looking
for attitude and aptitude
and really what we're looking for colleges
or how colleges can help build these.
Within our industry,
this kind of aligns with what AI is as well.
We're looking for people that can dig down
and find root cause,
like really understand the core failure
or reason for failure
so that we can improve the product.
So, how colleges can help us build these things,
some of the things I have down here is technicians that,
or technicians or people that treat knowledge
as a prize is really what we're looking for.
Like that's an ideal candidate profile for me.
Somebody that approaches learning something new
as really the thing that they're developing,
that thing they're striving for.
And then, along with that is a leveling-up mindset.
So, as I gain new information
and new ideas, like it allows me to gain access
to more complex systems.
And that's really the way we treat our entire workforce
with technicians is as an entry level technician,
you're expected some amount of efficiency and utilization
and specific job types.
And as you gain new information over years of experience,
now your scope grows, right?
Like the scope of work that you're required
to do within the industry expands
and now you have to do more.
You have to get involved in diagnostics
and work with engineering teams and all of the other things.
So again, to kinda go back, bring this all back
to the candidate profile we're looking for is somebody
that really looks at learning new things
and increasing the scope of work that they do
as the prize in and of itself.
And the other thing with that is the scope always grows,
we're looking for somebody
that doesn't have any jobs beneath them.
Just understand that as you continue
to gain momentum in your career,
like there's no jobs beneath you.
Like that's the profile that we're really looking for.
And how colleges can do this,
so some of the things that we've worked with
with colleges in the past are like hands-on efforts
are always going to be paramount.
Like really teaching the hands-on skills.
So, doing this through progressive lab challenges,
like starting simple and adding complexity.
A big part is kind of what you just touched on as well.
So, cross system projects showing
how everything connects together.
How is being an EV technician relevant
to being a traditional dealership technician?
And how is that relevant to being an HVAC technician
and how is that relevant to being, you know,
within any other industry?
It's all about transferable skills, diagnostic competitions.
So, making troubleshooting a game is a big thing
that we like to include
in all of our technical traits program classes as well.
We have them bug cars for the instructor
so that they can see the thought process change,
like it's a big part of it.
And then something that everybody enjoys.
And then just general learning portfolios
so that everybody can see their process and their progress
and understand how to have that level up
or achieve the next thing.
- Great, Tom, thank you. - Yep. Thank you.
- Blake, do you have some thoughts on that?
I could see it germinating your head. (laughs)
- Yeah, (exhales)
Yeah, I agree with so much of what Tom said.
I think that one thing
that I was thinking about is there seems to exist
some trepidation sometimes with new jobs, you know,
will I be qualified?
I think an important part to remember
is the counterpoint to that is,
as a company, when when we say,
"Oh, we need X amount of new jobs,"
we don't have anyone that's qualified to do that.
We don't. (laughs)
It's not like there's some secret cohort
of people that are trained and qualified and ready to go.
So, we are also looking for solutions
to the problem we have.
And ultimately as we look to break those out,
apply first principles thinking,
we really drill down to what is the problem we need to solve
and look for proxies, whether that is (claps)
submarine technicians or video game developers
or whatever the case may be.
We've had tremendous success from folks
that either were HVAC folks or mechanics
or even professional video game players
that have come to Nuro and applied those skills
in varying capacities toward AVs, right?
And I think that when there's also a lot
of emerging regulation that, of course,
we are not in front of or nobody's an expert in.
So, I think that the core fundamentals of curiosity
and being very passionate about finding solutions,
diagnostics, analytical rigor are very,
very important to keep in mind.
But the specificity with which those skills are applied
is less relevant, I think than the core skills themselves.
- And the other topic that you both touched on
was soft skills and working in a startup organization
is a very different dynamic
than going to a very structured bricks
and mortar dealership, for example.
So, if we could talk a little bit about
the special soft skills needed to not just survive
in a (laughs) startup, and I worked in a startup,
so I know you have to wear many different hats,
you gotta do a lot of different things.
What type of soft skills would you like to see
from our community college students
that would help them really thrive
in your startup environments?
- That's a really good question.
So, I think the first thing, you know,
when I think about soft skills,
I certainly think of, you know, project management
and timelines and communication and all of that good stuff.
And certainly at a startup, you know,
you need to be resilient
and you need to wear a number of different hats.
But I think the most important thing for a startup
at Nuro, there's 700 people in the company
and the people with whom you work,
you do so often and continuously.
And so, (titters) the first thing I'd say
about soft skills is we look for people
that we want to spend time with.
We look for people that we want to work with.
I promise you that if you are a cantankerous genius,
you will not work at Nuro, regardless of the problem
you can solve, the time or money you can save us.
It just doesn't matter.
It's just not worth it to work with people
who are not genuine, who are not caring,
who don't identify with the mission.
It's too hard a job to do,
to do it with people
whom you don't appreciate doing it with.
So, I think that's the first
and most important thing I would say is be someone
that people want to work with.
- Tom. - Yeah, yeah.
I don't know that I have much to add beyond that.
I mean, I think that's true for our industry as well.
It's just scaled up a little bit.
The one thing that we expect of our technicians
is to go to customer's houses
and fix vehicles in their driveway.
So, just to kind of add on to what was just said,
being able to convey information in an accurate way
is super important for us as well.
And like telling, talking to a customer
and explaining in enough detail that they understand
what was performed on their vehicle.
So, just having an understanding of the job
that was just performed, why they did it
and what the result is.
Yeah. - James?
(mic clanking)
- This is especially, from some of my previous experience,
I just wanted to stress,
these softer skills may be a little different.
They are equally as important in big legacy companies.
In particular with them,
I will say one of the most important things
is just what you were saying, being able to explain concepts
to non-technical people both inside
and outside of the company.
At Ford, all of my team was basically PhDs.
Biggest thing I had to work with them is you need
to be able to give a presentation
that a Ford senior executive will understand.
My day-to-day job ended up being explaining
very basic like first year master's level transportation
engineering concepts to C-suite people
because that's what needed to be done.
I now, at Berkeley, have the exact same experience
on the other side when I work with a bunch of companies.
So like, these are big companies, we're talking, you know,
big OEMs, big cell companies, et cetera, exact same thing.
Whenever they have like a super technical person,
who speaks in acronyms, in charge, it's a nightmare
to get anything done
because this is such a rapidly changing space,
you can't be the sort of person
who is an expert in their own little field
and doesn't want to go beyond it.
It just will not work anywhere
that I can think of in automation
or electric vehicles to be honest.
- So, I'm gonna switch gears a little bit to AI,
'cause AI is definitely a theme
that we're all thinking about today,
given this morning's discussions.
But in automotive, I was particularly interested
in finding out, okay,
what exactly are the car dealerships
and organizations looking at in terms
of AI skills and tools,
and what do our students need to know,
and how do we need to prepare them for that going forward?
And it's interesting, because when it comes to cars
that are on the roads today, they're very advanced machines
and many of them have already been built
with a lot of AI tools in the cars.
So, you have scan, you know,
the scan tools basically are doing most of the diagnostics.
And we've been teaching, you know,
scan tool technology at our schools now
for at least, oh, eight to 10 years.
So, that actually helps the students
because the scan tools actually read off
of the different sensors on all the systems in the car
to help them understand what is wrong with the car.
That gives the students extra time to really come up
with the diagnostics and to be creative in their diagnostics
and their communication with their students.
But at the same time, there's more going on,
there's more going on in that car
and predictive maintenance is out there.
There's all kinds of things happening.
So, I asked a couple of car dealerships
and these are traditional ICE cars,
these are not electric or autonomous.
What are their expectations
for our students in this particular category?
And they basically said they thought
that AI was gonna help more on customer service and sales
and the actual paperwork, you know, at the end of the day,
not necessarily operations and maintenance and repair.
But I thought I'd throw it out there
to see if Randy has any thoughts on this.
(Mic scuffling)
- So, the AI part is,
I found a very interesting observation this morning, right?
So, it's not really about how can we train people
to work in AI so they can be replaced by AI.
It's how do we make people retainable in their career fields
that will be impacted by AI.
So,
which, I made an observation this morning,
which job did you notice this morning
that's already been replaced by automation, AI automation?
It happened this morning.
Anybody notice it?
The translate, yes.
They no longer have sign language interpreters.
It's on the boards, right?
So, that's the first step.
That was just a big notice that I had today, right?
And so, one of my primary passions
is how do we keep people retainable in their career field?
How do we change what they're doing
to be able to manipulate the AI
or fix the robot
that's now putting the widget on the circuit board
instead of you?
How do we make that workforce retainable?
Because I like to think of it as not artificial intelligence
but intelligent assistant, right?
So, how do we make the workforce we have today
more efficient and able to use AI
and be able to retain their job?
As I had a person one time tell me, he was like, you know,
"I don't have to have a bookkeeper anymore.
I don't have to have a receptionist anymore.
I don't have to have all these people
working in my office anymore."
And it's like, "Well, think about what you just said.
So, you do this, whatever you do in this company,
who's gonna be there in 10 years to buy your product
if they don't have jobs?"
So, we have to retrain the workforce
to make them retainable, not replaceable.
That's my goal.
(mic scuffling)
- James.
- I'll make a slightly different point.
Totally in agreement.
AI is
a huge field.
I was just saying, "Oh, automation,
it can mean lots of things."
Order of magnitude, orders of magnitude bigger for AI.
So, and right now most of the AI that people interact
with on a day-to-day basis in the general public
are these LLMs, the ChatGPTs and stuff like that.
And those have definite applications,
but we're really talking about one pretty small subset
of the entire AI space.
So, I just want to be adamant
that AI will change everything,
but I'm not saying ChatGPT will change everything
'cause that's only one small portion of it.
So, some of those sort of things can be helping
say with sales and the like.
I think for me, the biggest area
that I'm really interested in is just what you were saying.
How can we use AI to be a force multiplier?
And this is, I'm sure you guys see this every day,
I see it all of the time at Berkeley.
My wife is a professor at UC, Riverside.
She teaches undergrads on a daily basis.
For her it's a real struggle because students now,
there's so much more that they need to learn.
Even compared to when I went to school.
I was like one of the last people, oh, you know, basic math,
basic science, basic writing.
I think I was one of the last people I had to hand write
one of my college essays.
They don't do that anymore for anyone.
But now it's like, oh, well,
you need to have a little bit of coding skills.
You need to have good computer skills,
you need to know how to give a presentation.
And this makes it hard for students
because they can't do absolutely everything.
I know with my wife, she's like, students come to her
so proud that they could write a five-page essay
and they didn't know that they could write
a five-page essay.
And it's easy for us to laugh at that
'cause we did that repeatedly when we were an undergrad.
But that's all that we had to do.
Being able to help with some of the day-to-day,
that's why I am excited about the soft skill stuff,
is usually beneficial
'cause this is what I see in my daily life too.
I'm like, I need to work with my team
and these are incredibly smart people
with PhDs from top universities,
but I have to work with them.
And you can just like, "Mine aren't that great either,"
but it's like, "Hey, dude, your presentations suck
and your writing sucks
and no one understands what you're saying
outside of about a dozen people in the world
and that's not your audience right now."
So, this is a universal problem,
but I can see AI being really, really helpful.
You know, you need to be able
to know what you're talking about.
You can't just use whatever PowerPoint presentation
your AI LLMs spits out,
but it can get you 90% of the way there
and let you be a lot more efficient at your job.
- James, thank you.
Are there any questions from the audience?
(mic humming)
Yes?
- [Audience Member] I just have a question for-
(mic scuffling drowns out speaker)
we have students now to be-
I work in services area
and now to hire someone
to do the work in the office,
it's no longer we have to look for something
that we were looking 10 years ago.
Now it's more skilled, right?
You have to work more with technology,
even you should know software,
and you should know applications, even some programming
and incidentally, the (indistinct) office.
- Yeah. - So, exactly, AI is not
gonna replace these people who are trained
and should be skilled to work with AI,
using AI as a tool, not as a replacement.
- Yeah, for me, it's been funny with,
I'm guessing you guys have seen this a lot,
but my friends, more in the private sector tech world,
so many, like almost all of them are so exci...
They all use AI for coding
because that's like one of the best applications
that it's really, really hard
and you still need to have that experience.
But like, oh man, you can be so much of a faster
and effective coder if you can rely on AI.
You don't have to do it all from scratch.
- Yeah.
- Any final comments from anyone?
(mic clanking)
- Yeah, I think one other thing
to think about in terms of AI
is technicians in the field no longer become the end user.
Really, it becomes about the story
that you're putting in, right?
So, if we can utilize AI for predictive maintenance
and understanding what problems are going to come about
because the vehicle hits a certain mileage or age or range
or wherever it's at, the technicians are becoming the people
that input that data to the AI, right?
They're the ones that are now building the database
that AI is learning from.
So, it's really important, again,
to go back to conveying information,
to accurately find the root cause of the issue
and accurately put that information into the system
so that AI can get better for the next iteration.
- Right.
And autonomous cars, let's face it, it's all generative AI.
The cars are learning machines
with AI built into it from the ground up.
So, what Nuro is doing is basically AI
and application form on four wheels.
So anyway, thank you all very much for attending this...
Oh, one last question.
- Let me ask him. - Oh, I'm sorry.
- Okay. - Oh, okay.
- It's okay. Times up. - It is.
I'm worrying about the time for you guys
to get to the next session. - Sorry, guys.
- But thank you all for attending
and thank you so much to our speakers.
(audience and panelists clapping)
- Thank you so much. - Thank you so much.
(audience clapping)